Mabel Cleland Widdemer Papers
Mabel Cleland Widdemer Papers
1921-1963
Widdemer, Mabel Cleland.
1.5 linear ft.
American poet and children's author. Collection contains correspondence, printed material, clippings, subject files. Note that the entire collection consists of photocopies (no original items).
3175655
Biographical History
Mabel Cleland Widdemer (1893-1964) was an American poet and children's author. She wrote several books for the "Childhood of Famous Americans" series published by Bobbs-Merrill, including biographies of Harriet Beecher Stowe, Washington Irving, James Monroe and DeWitt Clinton. Margaret Widdemer (1884-1978) was Mabel's sister-in-law; she was also an author and won a Pulitzer Prize for poetry.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Mabel Cleland Widdemer Papers includes correspondence, memorabilia, and writings. Note that the entire collection consists of photocopies (no original items).
Correspondence includes friends, relatives, publishers, fellow authors, and letters from readers.
Memorabilia contains clippings, letters, and transcripts of radio shows where Widdemer's work was discussed.
Writings contains articles, a few items of poetry, and assorted other items.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by name, title, or topic.
Related Material
See also the papers of her sister-in-law,
Margaret Widdemer
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Biography; Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Literature -- Children's; Women Authors; Tupper, Samuel, 1904-; Widdemer, Mabel Cleland.; Widdemer, Margaret.; Authors, American.; Children's authors.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Transcripts.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mabel Cleland Widdemer, 1962.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - American Boy, 1924 (Box 1)
  - American Girl, 1925-1935; 1946,; 1948,; 1950-1954,; undated; includes a folder of reader responses; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - American Library in Paris, 1946 (Box 1)
  - The American Magazine, 1932 (Box 1)
  - American Telephone & Telegraph, 1946-1947; 1952 (Box 1)
  - Arcadia House, 1928-1929; 1938,; 1940 (Box 1)
  - Atlantic Publications, 1928 (Box 1)
  - The Authors' Guild of the Authors' League of America, 1923; 1962 (Box 1)
  - Briggs, Olga Hampel, 1949-1950; 1954,; undated (Box 1)
  - Child Life, 1924-1928; 1938,; 1943 (Box 1)
  - The Classmate, 1926-1927; 1930,; 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - Cleland, Mabel, undated (Box 1)
  - Collier's, 1926; undated (Box 1)
  - Detroit Public Library, 1953-1954; undated (Box 1)
  - Doubleday & Company, 1948; 1952,; 1959,; 1963 (Box 1)
  - Eugene Field Society, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Everygirl's, 1926-1928 (Box 1)
  - Farrar & Rinehart, 1931-1934; undated (Box 1)
  - Fleming H. Revell Company, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Graves, Ralph H., 1939-1941 (Box 1)
  - Greene, Nelson, 1949-1951; undated (Box 1)
  - Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1924-1928; 1935,; 1938,; undated (Box 1)
  - Harold Ober Associates, 1953-1956 (Box 1)
  - Holland Society of New York, 1949 (Box 1)
  - The Household Magazine, 1928 (Box 1)
  - International Mark Twain Society, 1946; 1950 (Box 1)
  - J. B. Lippincott, 1922; 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Life, 1921-1924 (Box 1)
  - The Lyric, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Music Corporation of America, 1939 (Box 1)
  - New Fiction Publishing Corporation, 1921-1923 (Box 1)
  - New York Association for the Blind, 1933; 1936,; 1948,; 1952 (Box 1)
  - The New Yorker, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Pen and Brush, 1948; 1951,; 1954 (Box 1)
  - The Portal, 1924-1938; undated (Box 1)
  - Rand McNally & Company, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Reynolds, Noyes, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt Memorial Association, 1950-1952 (Box 1)
  - St. Nicholas, 1932-1938; undated (Box 2)
  - Saturday Evening Post, 1923; 1927-1928,; undated (Box 2)
  - Saturday Review of Literature, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Stowe, Lyman Beecher, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Tupper, Sam Jr., 1958; undated (Box 2)
  - Twentieth Century Fox Film Corporation, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Weaver, Stella, 1949; 1952,; undated (Box 2)
  - Westminster Press, 1944-1945; 1952 (Box 2)
  - Who's Who, 1941; 1961 (Box 2)
  - Widdemer, Margaret, 1981-1919; 1951-1954,; 1957-1963,; undated; letters to and from Mabel's sister-in-law (Box 2)
  - Women's National Book Association, 1932-1933 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, A-Z, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous fan letters (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Clippings, 1923-1960; undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - "A Letter from an Author", letter by Widdemer to a sixth grade book club (Box 2)
  - Material relating to Margaret Widdemer (Mabel's sister-in-law) (Box 2)
  - "Notes for my talk and for publicity purposes in connection with reading to the children at the Albany celebration", June 21st, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Radio show transcripts
    - The Book Column, with Olga Briggs, WPTR Albany, 1949-1950 (Box 2)
    - The Book Mark, with Olga Briggs, WABY Albany, 1949-1950; 1958 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Writings
  - A-U, 3 folders (Box 3)